hey guys welcome to episode number 36 of
the future thinkers podcast today our
guest is Daniels Martin Berger Daniel is
an evolutionary philosopher strategist
and social engineer his work focuses on
complex systems the evolution of
humanity and global resource allocation
his goal is to find the shortest path to
a fundamentally redesigned world system
that supports in an ongoing way the
highest quality of life for everybody on
the planet he specifically focuses on
developing economic and governmental
systems that by design incentivize life
enhancing behavior Daniels recent
project is neuro hacker collective which
is a smart drug brand with a vision of
holistic human optimization in this
episode Daniel talks about many deep and
fascinating ideas to do with building a
better future for all of humanity he
specifically talks about the different
systems we will need to transition into
this new world and to mitigate
existential risks this is a really great
episode I think it's one of our
favorites if you want all the shownotes
books and mentions from this episode go
to future thinkers org slash 36 before
we get into it as always I want to thank
our recent patrons and donors Diana
Pascal rich and Nigel thank you guys for
making this show happen you're awesome
all right here's the show welcome to
future thinkers org a podcast about the
evolution and technology society and
consciousness I'm Mai Gilliland and I'm
UV Ivanova this episode is brought to
you by eternity the Oracle machine
eternity is a new blockchain platform
for smart contracts with a token crowd
sale launching in March 2017 go to
future thinkers org slash eternity and
subscribe to their mailing list to get
notified when it goes live to get
notified of new podcasts and videos go
to future thinkers org and subscribe to
our mailing list you can also find us on
iTunes stitcher and you tube if you like
what we do and you want to help us make
more podcasts and videos give us a like
or review share it with your friends and
consider becoming a patron go to
patreon.com/crashcourse slash bap
Daniel welcome to the show thank you so
much for joining us so we're gonna have
a lot of things to talk about today but
why don't we start by talking about an
optimistic future of humanity and what
we need to do to transition into that
future there are a lot of visions and
theories out there about the ultimate
macro system that we need to adopt not
only to survive the century but to
thrive what is your vision of that first
I wouldn't talk in terms of an ultimate
system talk in terms of ongoing
evolution and so rather than kind of a
utopian as one has previously thought of
a perfected system we're going to think
of a proto pian process right a process
of emergence into more elegantly ordered
complexity that has more and more
emergent properties and more of the
things we're interested in and gets over
some of the underlying causes of things
we want to get past I would say that
rather than just iterative evolution we
are on the brink of a phase shift and
phase shift defined by core axioms and
core foundations of most of our macro
global systems from our worldview to our
economics to our governance to our
infrastructure going through
foundational shifts so this looks like a
step function in evolution where we have
had capitalism that has gone through
kind of iterative developmental
processes and we've had representative
democracy that's gone through iterative
developmental processes and you know
scientific methodology and worldview and
etc now we are on the brink of something
that requires larger more fundamental
axiomatic and structural shift and so we
can talk about what the criteria for the
other side of that have to look like for
it to be a non-self terminating system
and for it to be a anti fragile system
and those are two of the important
criteria of any kind of world that is
interesting for anyone right
it is definitely non-self terminating
and then not anti fragile then there's
more things we'll talk about on top of
that so you want to talk about what
those criteria must be well sure but
first let's define the problem so what's
wrong with our current system and why do
we
to transition out of it so when we say
our current system we are sweeping a lot
of things together and it's worth kind
of pulling those apart a bit we might be
talking about macroeconomics which
obviously the macroeconomics of China
and the macroeconomics of Russia the
macroeconomics of the United States if
NATO are different systems but there are
kind of beyond national global economic
systems that we can we can look at we
can look at governance systems again
national and then transnational
governance and then beyond anything
that's codified how human
decision-making works right we can think
of governance in the highest sense of
how do we do collective decision-making
at various scales from a business to a
family to a nation to groups of Nations
to a species as a whole navigating
things that face the whole species
economics we can think about how do we
do resource allocation and how do we do
human incentive systems with
infrastructure we can talk about how do
we meet our physical needs and
relationship with the physical planet
right education medicines we have a lot
of different systems that Co evolved and
they are interconnected and Entering and
then you can think of a you know kind of
evolving paradigm that involves all of
those things but we're gonna need to
talk about at least the core ones in
distinction from each other so what is
the problem we're trying to fix well one
thing is those current systems the
interface of those current systems with
each other and the net effects are
unsustainable and unsustainable means
self terminating means that these
systems run to their own end and then
fall off some kind of cliff right and so
when we look at growth curves of
different kinds of organisms anytime we
see a growth curve that has an
exponential up that is not forever
and sometimes the exponential up goes
logistic and that's very nice sometimes
it drops off pretty hard before it
logistics sometimes it goes through a
lot of unstability you sometimes just
Exponential's up and then drops off a
cliff right so we were under half a
billion popularly
for all of human history as far as we
know 200 plus thousand years until the
Industrial Revolution and then in just
over 200 years we went up to over 7
billion people and growing and that is a
profound exponential population curve
not only have we went through this
profound exponential population curve in
relationship to our ability to extract
resources from the planet that are not
replenishing themselves which is what
the Industrial Revolution was right
mining farming fishing logging etc the
ability to take some kind of resource
reserves that took hundreds of millions
or billions of years to develop and to
be able to extract them at a radically
fast pace and obviously much faster than
they can renew and then the population
is growing on that savings account until
you hit the end of a savings account and
then there's real problems not only have
we been growing in population but we've
been growing in resource consumption per
capita so this is a multiplicative issue
that we are getting near the end of the
viability of that particular part of
right when we think about running an
economy it requires a year-over-year
growth requires it because your
fractional izing the monetary supply
even deeper than that just interest
where the monetary supply has to
fundamentally expand right then to not
debase the currency you have to increase
the total amount of goods and services
services sit on top of product economies
which relate to a linear materials
economy product materials economy which
the linear materials economy means
extracting resources from the planet
unruhe notably which means devastation
of ecosystems and things like that and
then turning them into trash in ways
that usually consume a good bit of
energy from dirty sources create a lot
of pollution and externalize harm to
people environments along the way you
know and then end with waste so that
kind of exponential growth economy and
attach to a linear materials economy
just doesn't work ongoing Leon
my planet right it only would work
ongoingly on an infinite playing field
which were not on and so that is a
fundamentally self terminating system it
makes plenty of sense that when there
was just so much low-hanging fruit in
terms of coal and oil and fish and trees
and etc that we would do this
exponential boom kind of thing it's just
that's not viable anymore
it also happens to be that the
technologies that would allow us to be
really viable in a post growth economic
system it's not about net more
consumption but about using the same
things in a closed-loop materials
economy in ever more interesting ways so
a materials economy that is closed-loop
post growth and upcycling continuously
upcycling the technology it takes to do
that is technology we are just now
getting happens to be that that's at the
same time that we are just now getting
to the point of self-determination of
the old system right so we both have to
shift and can at the same time the
technologies it takes to build this kind
of sustainable regenerative thriving new
set of world systems is technology that
we developed via capitalism and linear
materials economy and the military
industrial complex and all those things
so they served in evolutionary relevance
in terms of where we're going and they
have just completed a particular
evolutionary relevant lifecycle now
we're going through a discrete phase
shift into a new life cycle very much
like a fetal time period right in the
embryonic time period is unsustainable
the caterpillar can't just keep
devastating its ecosystem without
pollinating forever but that's not how
it works
and the baby couldn't stay in the belly
after 40 weeks and parasitically but
that's not how it works
it is going through a period where its
system is fundamentally not capable of
the kinds of autonomy that it will later
be capable of so it's a finite
evolutionary period of unsustainable
development to then go through a
discrete phase shift to then be in a
fundamentally new period and so I think
it's a very fair analogy to look at
humanity as having been
the kind of embryonic period Bucky
fuller used to like to speak to it like
that like a you know chicken embryo
having finished eating the egg white on
renewable resources emerge from a world
it didn't know it was in right emerge
from the shell into a world where that
it now has a beak to eat that it didn't
have before when I was eating the egg
whites come from plants that it's poop
fertilizes and it's part of this larger
kind of regenerative process they
evolved so when we talk about what the
problem is our materials economy is
unsustainable our macroeconomic
structures themselves or ideas of
ownership and valuation and etc are all
fundamentally unsustainable they're
coming up on the cliffs of
unsustainability are exponentially
increasing tech curves are creating more
and more existential threats etc right
so this is all what we would call self
terminating and even before we get into
existential and catastrophic risks it's
also already causing suffering at just
such massive scales whether we're
talking about you know war and drum
strikes on civilians or whether we're
talking about factory farms that are
these just rolling apocalypses or
whether we're talking about fishing the
oceans down to nearly nothing or with we
can forecast future catastrophic
scenarios but we're in them
right we're in these rolling
catastrophes moving towards complete
unviable 'ti and so the future systems
were interested in have to prevent total
existential risk and total catastrophic
risk they have to solve the foundational
causes of the current unnecessary human
induced suffering and then create world
systems that make possible and probable
and induce higher quality of life across
all the very meaningful quality of life
metrics for all life and optimize
evolutionary rate it seems like most
people are saying capitalism is what's
gotten us here and you're just taking a
couple extra steps to see where it
results you know a plus B equals C or
when we proposed basic income in the
past that's usually their answer well
capitalism has got us this far why would
it not take us further you think about
that embryo that baby growing in the
mother's belly
and if you didn't know that it was a
baby that was going to birth at a
certain point it would be easy to
mistake it as a very serious parasite
yes because it's it is taking a lot of
nutritional load from her body right it
is modifying her physiology profoundly
and if you imagine a mom in the eight to
nine months if you didn't know that
there was a discrete phase shift about
to happen you'd be pretty sure she was
very near dying in a pretty terrible way
this is the difference between a
parasite and a baby is that the baby
goes to that for a finite period and
then phase shifts into a different phase
right interestingly when we look at
parasitology biology vector ology there
are many parasites that when they
initially start feeding on an animal
human whatever and they haven't before
they kill them fairly quickly the ones
that were aggressive enough to kill the
hosts quickly don't propagate right
because they killed their host they
don't live very long they don't get to
travel on to many other hosts the milder
versions that don't actually kill their
hosts get to both live longer and
propagate more and so there are a number
of pathogens that get less toxic over an
evolutionary time frame because they
have to be we don't get the chance of
killing lots of planets to figure out
you know we could do it that way that
only the planets where the people were
less problematic in this way and that
making it through but we want to do a
more conscious version than that right
and so rather than the slow evolution of
a parasite to be less pathologic we need
to do the actually going through a birth
into a new phase model and we can what's
so fascinating is that if we define a
civilization where we have a sustainable
population that does not require
imposition from the outside some kind of
eugenics program or Chinese births
limiting program whatever it is a
emergent self-organizing phenomena and
we've already seen plenty of places in
the world where when education gets high
enough economics and female empowerment
and etc that population stabilizes can
even decrease to find the right levels
of where it's at we've seen
Japan we've seen it in some of the
Scandinavian countries and so to have a
steady-state population that is within
the sustainable carrying capacity of the
planet connected to a post growth
materials economy where the materials
that we are using are being designed in
a cradle-to-cradle way where they're
recyclable 'ti after this particular use
is built right in there's no such thing
as waste there's just moving the old
stuff back into new stuff the new stuff
is being made from old stuff so it
doesn't require virgin resource
acquisition the only new thing coming
into the system and doesn't mean we
won't ever take a new thing into the
system as far as atoms go we could we
find an asteroid with some interesting
platinum we could do that or but we have
a system that doesn't require trash or
extraction right that's what post growth
means is post necessity for growth so
that it actually can be sustainable
viable and then we just keep increasing
the efficiency of how we utilize those
resources and attenuating the forms that
they're in the only resource that we
keep bringing into the system
continuously is energy because that's
what we keep having ongoing access to so
we have new photons coming in all the
time we don't have new atoms coming in
all the time these new photons coming in
all the time allows us to keep recycling
the atoms where we're upcycling them
rather than downcycling them because
this is not a closed system right we get
to externalize entropy out of the system
bring you know enough energy to keep
driving more central people in the
system so when we ask what are the
necessary and sufficient criteria of a
sustainable non self terminating
thriving anti fragile world that does
obsolete the catastrophic and
existential risks the current cause of
suffering and create higher qualities of
life we could actually do this
construction in detail sometime but I'll
just kind of state the things as far as
infrastructure goes our physical
relationship with the physical world it
does require these three criteria
closed-loop post growth and upcycling
right negative entropy but it's not
actually negative into pre no
thermodynamics sense because we're
bringing energy into the system as far
as social systems go economics
governance
law language right the social
agreement fields by which we navigate
collective agreement collective
decision-making collective resource
allocation all the things beyond just
individual action we can think of
governance as how we make decisions that
involve Co decision-making collaborative
decision-making most all of the
decisions we're going to make are going
to involve allocating resources of some
kind some way so we think of economics
as how we allocate resources and the
other major thing that economics has
done is human incentives so when there's
a bunch of shitty jobs that nobody if
they didn't have to would want to spend
all of their life doing maybe I'll pave
a road a little bit now and again but I
don't want to spend 40 hours a week my
entire life until retirement doing that
as long as we have shitty jobs
especially in the labor economy that the
society needs done for the quality of
life that is related to infrastructure
then we need to get the people to do the
jobs Adam Smith talked about this Marx
did everybody did right it's the core of
economic theory so if you do some kind
of communism where everyone's needs are
met by the system then how do you get
the people to do their shitty jobs well
then the state has to force them and we
call that imperialism is why we don't
like communism right or everyone has to
do an equal amount but that's still the
who is gonna enforce that state that's
important so capitalism says no no we'll
let the free market enforce them right
which is if they don't do the shitty
jobs they just go homeless that's really
not freedom
still it just moved the forcing function
from the state to market right well as
we're moving into technological
automation this foundational axiom of
all economic theories which is how do we
deal with the labor economy right is the
this is an axiomatic topic is being
obsoleted we're up sleeting that all of
the conversations that Marx and Smith
and friends had and so that both solves
problems and it brings new ones so when
we have technological automation that is
capable of automating the shitty jobs
and it's important to get when I say
that that doesn't mean that the machines
are going to take your jobs and you
can't garden if you want to
in garden or washer toilet if
you want to you just don't have to wash
your toilet all the time because we can
make bathrooms that clean themselves
better right and then if you just want
to do that you're welcome to human
freedom can absolutely do that if you
want a garden you're welcome to do that
but can we create vertical agriculture
systems that automate many aspects of
that while providing high-quality
nutritious food with lower impact on the
environment yes we can right and that
opens up more human freedom not that's
the other so as long as we have a
situation where the jobs need the people
then we have to make it where the people
also need the jobs ie capitalism right
which is why that system has you know
succeeded in a Darwinian sense in the
way that it has it's important to get
that Darwinian selection does not select
for the true the good and the beautiful
right it selects for what is adaptive
which means what is dominant within
scarcity dynamics now even if that's
gonna you know be going extinct in the
very near future because it's not
forecasting it's not adequately
forecasting right as soon as you can
make it to where the jobs don't need the
people the automation you can also make
it where the people don't need the jobs
which is what the Commonwealth economics
is moving towards in a first step in the
direction is the basic income basic
income is not enough but it is a step
and the key for it not to be a welfare
system when we think about the problems
of the welfare system and how you have
people who don't have the Darwinian
motive to create that capitalism gave
them so they just sit on the couch and
smoke crack all day those are people
that have already been broken this is a
very important point when you look at
little children they're asking questions
all day long why is fire hot why is the
sky blue
where do we go after we die where do you
know they're fascinated asking deep
philosophic and physics and you know etc
questions and they want to help do stuff
and they want to build stuff and they
and then we don't answer those questions
because why the is fire hot that's
actually a very deep physics question
and then it's moving from physics to
consciousness studies let the mind brain
interface of subjective experience of
hotness with
on the skin and nerve pathways and so we
say I don't know spell cat and we don't
facilitate their interests while forcing
them to be interested in completely
uninteresting and thereby breaking
their interest in life so then they just
want to veg the out right and so
now we have broken humans or if they can
just veg out they will but this is not
human nature this is broken humans in a
system that systematically breaks humans
and so it's very important to get that
in this kind of economic system that
we're proposing there's a fundamentally
different education system that's
possible because we don't have to
prepare kids for the workforce and since
we don't prepare them for the workforce
the whole goal of education becomes
identifying the unique aptitude and
interest and fascination and inclination
of each child and facilitating the
out of it and realizing that they don't
have to actually be able to do
everything because we've automated a lot
of things and then we've shared a lot of
things right but what they can uniquely
do and what they can light up the most
and uniquely doing and then have the
benefit of that being fully available to
everyone in a Commonwealth economics
that makes radically more abundance
possible then for everyone then is
actually possible for anyone in this
system I'll come back to explaining how
that's possible then that's the goal of
Education right facilitating the
emergence of radical uniqueness when I
think about what is required in this
post-birth sort of society I'm going to
call it I think people are optimizers so
it's more like picking the route or
direction that they want to go to and
then make that part of the system more
efficient over time like I myself do
that with every aspect of our lives with
our website with you know I'm like an
efficiency optimizer no doubt people
when they find what their calling is
what they want to be doing they're gonna
spend a lot of time doing exactly that
in in the grander scale the way you say
the incentives are all out of whack yeah
D motivates them to learn which in turn
D motivates them to optimize anything
which is exactly what this new system
needs and since you identify as an
optimizer
then you think of it through the lens of
that they'll all be optimizing that's a
good lens
someone else would say that they will
all be creating yeah that's me
wow they map to each other there they're
both different experiences
phenomenologically and they actually are
different parts of the creative
lifecycle and etc right different modes
you also have some people who identify
things that they're particularly
passionate about where all of the topics
they're passionate about kind of braid
together into a very clear through line
and there will be other people for whom
that's much less clear that are more
focused on interpersonal connection and
depth of subjective experience and the
creative process itself independent of
any particular result that's being
produced and one of the beautiful things
is that's not possible in a
macroeconomic system where you say how
do you turn that into the dollars you
need to live in a macroeconomic system
where that's not the question
there is a important difference between
appreciable wealth and exchangeable
wealth when we think about a rainbow
it's not extractable and exchangeable
wealth for anyone seeing a rainbow when
you think about hearing a song when you
think about somebody complimenting you
seeing a smile like none of these are
things you can put on the balance sheet
in any metrical way but when you think
about what makes life most rich it's
largely these things that fit into
appreciable but not quantifiable wealth
and so one of the beautiful things that
happens when the primary balance sheet
that we're paying attention to is the
balance sheet of the Commons the natural
world Commons and the built world
Commons that everyone has access to
without possessing is that we have a
system that gets to start optimizing for
appreciable wealth generation because
we're not only focused on exchangeable
wealth accounting systems I think we're
already seeing that a little bit with
the Internet where people are producing
you know they're producing music they're
making memes they're writing blogs but
they're not really most of the time
they're not expecting to make money from
it they're just doing it because it's
exciting for them or they they get some
sort of satisfaction out of just
producing it and putting it out there
and it's accessible to the world
the Internet now while those people
still have to work their day job to
support themselves and then they're
gonna come to their music and their day
job might happen to be something that
they experience is relatively
soul-crushing in terms of possibilities
they know how to access then they come
to that little bit of music you think
about what would happen if we just
supported them to be in the position to
do music as deeply as they could wanted
to right
and what if they didn't have to try and
gear it towards what was sellable so
that they could then switch from the
soul-crushing to the money-making music
but what was really authentically what
they felt was their greatest offering
you know their most unique offering we
had a very different kind of creativity
happening one of the issues right now we
see in this kind of post fact world
where what is fake news and what is not
fake news and what one of the issues of
the inability to make sense of almost
anything that we're facing is how much
of any news that you find or any idea
has some financial interest associated
with it how much education is an
advertorial
you know in some way how much of science
itself is actually just the R&D arm of
capitalism funded by something that has
a vested interest attached and so this
is a very tricky process right where
what we can actually believe in and then
how much of music is geared towards what
is going to have the right kinds of
frames for me mobility so that it can
get puppy enough to sell Pepsi or
whatever rather than what is actually
what someone most authentically wants to
create that other people's most
authentically want to experience you
think about what it means to create
systems that remove all of those other
agendas so that there are no vested
interest agendas so now you know we
talked about that the criteria from
infrastructure what that had to be
here's the criteria for social systems
we said governance is decision-making
economics is decision making an
incentive but we just started to kind of
hint at that the incentive moves from
primarily extrinsic incentive to
intrinsic incentive and you have a
system that's all about facilitating in
trend
generative incentive right which D
necessitates most of extrinsic incentive
which becomes key then economics is
largely about resource allocation
systems optimization of resource
allocation towards all the various goals
that matter
so most decision-making in you know
governance is around resource decisions
law is how do we make sure that those
decisions actually get follow through so
we can actually think of economics as
the heart of social systems right so the
key criteria for the future of
macroeconomics is that all the
externalities get internalized meaning
everything that we affect by a decision
is factored in the decision making
process and the process by which
resources get conferred to things so
another way to say this is that the
agency the incentive of every agent
whether it's a person or a group of
people called a company or a country
even though I believe both of those two
things will become obsolete just think
any person or group of people any agent
the incentive of that agent has to be
perfectly aligned with the well-being of
every other agent and of the Commons as
a whole the degree to which the
individual agents are incentivized to do
something that is external izing harm to
other agents of the Commons is the
degree to which those problematic
externalities will continue to happen to
acquit ously in a decentralized fashion
at scale because they are incentivized
in decentralized fashion at scale that's
the key of the future of macroeconomics
is the alignment of agency and
well-being from individuals and Commons
and that correlates with closing the
loop right we talked about linear
materials economy moving to a closed
loop one right in the same way here
we're closing the loop between agency of
individuals well-being of others right
all the externalities being internalized
is moving from an open loop system where
I could affect things but not
internalize those effects in the cost
equation - now all internalized in the
cost equation and then that corresponds
to a world view where my sense of self
and my sense of the rest of universe are
not fundamentally separate concepts that
I wouldn't exist without oxygen
at all it wouldn't exist without the
plants that make the oxygen I wouldn't
exist without the bugs and the fungus
that make the plants work to make the
oxygen I I am not an individual I do
happen to have a self-organizing
membrane that has some individuality to
it but I am an emergent property of
everything else so when you close the
loop between sense of self and sense of
other then what's in my best interest
what's in the best interest of others
also there's a loop closure between
advantage self at the expense of others
or sacrifice self for the well-being of
others both of which are nonsense a
radically interconnected system so what
we're looking at is how we close all the
causal loops so that every thing that
influences decision making is being
informed by everything being influenced
that sounds like quite a spiritual
proposition also it relates to some of
the ideas that I've heard for example
Ken Wilber talking about sure where this
kind of evolution of the system and
evolution of the self converge
I believe I actually have the quadrants
on the whiteboard behind me from a
conversation earlier ultimately so if
we'll just use the quadrants from
integral philosophy for a moment when we
were talking about the evolution of
infrastructure we're talking about the
lower right hand quadrant right the
plural not just single right external so
all the physical infrastructure is the
physicality of the collective when we're
talking about social structures we're
talking about the lower left which is
the interior right the agreement fields
that we agreed to use this word to
symbolize this experience of this
meaning we agreed to denote this value
to these things we agreed to make
decisions in this way is the lower left
upper left is our individual value
system or worldview our internal
singular process language is affected by
Education and Culture and media and etc
the per right would be human physiology
and we usually think of physiology as
nature and the other three collectively
as nurture the other three can change
and collectively make up culture which
is nurture which is in conditioning the
expression of genetic
disposition because we are of course
changing radically one generation to the
next matically much faster than we're
changing genetically but that's not an
adequate way to think of it because
physiology can actually affect human
experience in human predisposition
radically independent of just genome
change through natural selection
everyone who's had their hormones off
knows that you can have be incapable of
accessing certain emotions or incapable
of being out of other emotion trader
when you said their neural chemistry
deeply off or just been very sick or
tired has known certain cognitive
abilities can shut down or other ones be
you know over predisposed so when you
realize that empathy runs on certain
neural networks and that can be down
regulated or up regulated right complex
thinking runs in certain kinds of neural
processes and if those are damaged or
not developed it can lead to
fundamentalism and only being able to
see something one way from a hardware
point of view not just a mimetic point
of view right and you can also up
regulate the kind of connect Tomic
complexity that leads to more net
information processing and
perspective-taking so what has to happen
in the upper right so we can think about
that the upper quadrants as being about
the individual the upper right is kind
of the hardware of the individual the
upper left is the software of the
individual right so you can think about
human physiology and then human mimetics
worldview values definition of success
psyche right as the software but of
course it's a place where there the
software and hardware not as distinct as
there are in computer systems every
software change is actually plastically
changing the hardware and vice versa the
hardware's predisposing software so that
you can see the analogy but also its
limit then you can think of the lower
quadrants where the lower right is
actually the hardware of the collective
infrastructures the hardware of the
collective and the social systems of the
software of the collective those for the
hardware and software of the individual
and the collective
is one taxonomy that is necessary and
sufficient for understanding human
experience in human behavior so there
are things that condition human behavior
in the upper right physiologic
predisposition
for human behavior predispositions for
feeling more depressed feeling happier
feeling you know having more empathy
less etc there are mimetic
predispositions for behavior religions
value systems trauma etc there are
economic and cultural predispositions
for behavior right as long as that
old-growth redwood tree is worth a
hundred thousand dollars cut down as
timber but it's worth nothing alive on
my balance sheet in that economic that
extraction arey non appreciable
recognizing economic system is going to
lead to cutting all the damn trees down
which we've seen and the same with the
whale being worth a million dollars on a
fishing boat but worth nothing alive in
the ocean right like the economics
conditions human behavior and
infrastructure actually conditions you
in behavior it's just a interesting but
important point it ends up being not net
neutral mimetic aliy right if you have a
infrastructure where the only way to get
electricity is from coal which we know
is causing an egg's or Bihar to other
life right mountaintop removal mining
mercury in the ocean whatever but we
need electricity to live you cannot have
full empathy in that infrastructural
system you actually have to
down-regulate your empathy to justify
getting long and even though you'll want
to not look at certain pictures and
videos when they come across because you
know you're contributing new things you
actually can't really handle
contributing to so you'll turn down your
awareness you'll change your behavior
you'll turn down empathy because
infrastructure is actually predisposing
patterns of mimetics and behavior right
so all four of those quadrants are
irreducible to each other but inter
effecting so if we have solutions that
are in any quadrant only they will be
inadequate and what you try and do in
any quadrant will necessarily affect and
be affected by the other ones so if we
want to think about civilization it's
not civilization design because we're
not talking about top-down architecture
it's the design of processes that lead
to emergence right if we want to think
about civilization birth midwifing right
it is supporting the emergence of a
viable self or
healthy resilient civilization we think
about the foundational shifts that have
to happen in each of those quadrants and
you know we mentioned most of them
involve closing open loops so that our
decision-making is Omni considerate our
decision-making ends up being in the
highest good of all that is being
affected by the decision what are some
of the more pressing loops that need
closing right now in your opinion
especially moving into 2017 what's
happening in the world right now what's
happening in the states with the u.s.
elections 2017 one of the things that we
see is a system a political system that
has been breaking and really broken for
some time having more complete and
obvious breakage and so we see a
Democratic Party that has all of the
kind of vested interests that it has
co-evolved with and you know damaged
structures that it has having supported
one of the least well-liked candidates
in recent history and anti supported one
of the most well liked candidates in
recent history resulting you know in its
failure the Republican Party failed to
have any really adequate candidates come
forward and so a candidate that
represented change by being outside of
the system won even though in so many
ways represented regressive change and
so the two-party system as a whole broke
each of the major platforms broke and
we're a very relatively small percentage
of people in the United States used to
know that there was real corruption
involved in the political process a much
higher percentage of people know that
now and have less faith that just going
to the polls and voting is an adequate
solution to the revolution that they
might hope happens
what that portends for future election
cycles and also how people start to have
civic engagement independent of
elections is all interesting right
you know Trump is a very interesting
person in this position with the cabinet
that's coming because there's plenty of
really concerning things right there's
plenty of really concerning things in
terms of the embolden
be guitry that has already been here you
know so deeply but that in being brought
to the light and the surface and and
embolden that way is both more
concerning more problematic but also
more capable of being healed because
it's more obvious represents an
existential catastrophic view on the
climate and energy but is also starting
to be surrounded by some people that
have meaningfully better perspectives
like Elon Musk and others so hopefully
there is influence potential there but
we also see things like really seeking
to remove people from office who have
had crony capitalists ties for such a
long time and propose things like
auditing the Fed that are actually
revolutionary revolutionary and in a
good way and so it's very interesting to
see what could happen
over the next time hear it here but what
we're seeing is let's let's look at it
from a larger sense because similar
things are happening in other places in
the world right not just in politics but
in the failure of several developed
countries economic systems and you know
etc if you think about it in terms of
systems theory and complex adaptive
systems there's a kind of foundational
principle that says complexity will
evolve within any organizational system
inexorably just because there's movement
and with movement there are self
interacting dynamics and that's going to
lead to increased complexity right and
so complex is going to evolve within any
organizational system until it actually
exceeds that organization
systems capacity to manage and when it
exceeds it you're gonna start getting
increased chaos and then increased
entropy and then the dissolution of that
organizational system and then you're
either going to get the entropic
step-down to the previous level of
organization or out of the chaos you get
the emergence of a higher level of
organization that isn't a retrofit of
the previous system but a fundamentally
new kind of system that's a place that
globally I would say we're at we have
you know representative democracy is
just fundamentally not capable of
handling the kinds of collaborative
decision-making we need to make right
now when you think about the founding of
the United States and the time when
people would get together in a town hall
without representative decision-making
right they get together and all vote on
something and then someone would have to
be represent the whole group who's gonna
ride a horse to where all the other town
halls met to decide what the state did
err it made sense to have
representatives for very real
technologic limits you know and there
were other reasons that were argued but
that was a part of the etiology of the
whole thing right and then when you
couldn't have a town hall big enough for
the whole population and so we have an
Internet
Town Hall beginning for the whole
population nobody has to ride a horse we
have we we don't need the
representatives in the same way we have
people that actually have real topic
matter expertise it can be groups of
decentralized peer-to-peer mavens that
can actually make relevant decisions
based on real knowledge of how those
kinds of systems work connected with the
data and the facts you know necessary
we've and we've already seen these kind
of peer-to-peer systems do better
decision-making at the scale of
complexity there operating than a
representative democratic system one so
you know that system served evolutionary
relevance but it is obsolete and if you
think about it could you have
representative democracy we have people
in positions of legislative power where
those people are still
within capitalism who need to advantage
themselves within capitalism as as
individuals and members of families
could you have representative democracy
and capitalism together and not have it
become crony capitalism well we have
never seen it happen and it's just a
structural thing it's not just
particular bad people right it's just
structural you have a system where you
incentivize people to acquire stuff and
then you put people in a position to
legislate in the interest of things that
they're more interested in and you know
that that's going to happen right so
capitalism and you know an economic
system that externalizes as much harm to
the Commons as possible right and where
your profit margin is actually
proportional to how much harm you can
externalize that pits all different
kinds of people against each other in
ways that keep enmity unavoidable you
know a linear materials economy that is
devastating the past fear that we live
on across the entire thing like so that
whole system
it wasn't self terminating when the
complexity was low enough that we had a
billion people and we cut trees down
with access but with the kinds of
industrial fishing boats that can just
trawl the entire ocean with slash and
burn with ICBM you know and seven
billion of us that same kind of mindset
we had becomes very quickly extinction
area and so the the scope of our power
the complexity of our problems the
number of us are making those systems
fail now we can think of this as the
baby at the end right the complexity of
its being kept growing which meant more
and more cells which meant a bigger baby
until it was at the end of how big it
could fit in there and never get out of
the birth canal which triggered the
contractions for it to come out right
now sometimes the mom and baby died in
the birth process that can happen but if
it's supported properly then rather than
die in the birth process you get
discrete phase shift into the next phase
of evolution and that's exactly where I
see us at over the next you know from an
evolutionary time period very small
period of time which is the ability to
have the evolu
and emergence of systems that support a
globally interconnected human
civilization that is actually on the
asset side of nature's balance sheet
rather than on the liability side so
what kind of things can we do as a
civilization to kind of aid in that
midwifery process to allow for this baby
to be born any of the places where you
can help close major open loops and then
do it in ways that can lead to
scalability are things worth looking at
so if you think about infrastructure the
ability to change production and waste
management manufacturing to a
closed-loop process so you start
thinking about could we have
decentralized systems of 3d 4d printing
with modular upgradability built in
rather than designed in obsolescence and
proprietary nonsense built in and
cradle-to-cradle design built in and
then have them connected to recycling
systems that move to lower entropy and
higher efficiency moving eventually
towards things like atomic sorting where
then the old things get to be brought
back into the individual parts to make
new things all run on renewable energy
sources low toxicity low entropy
renewable energy sources on the biologic
side of that the stem cell meet the
vertical farming the synthetic biology
as part of the you know creative
materials process and then the waste
management of the organic fractions it
involves anaerobic digestion algae
scrubbers etc and so there is no waste
there is no raw material sourcing that
isn't part of that closely building
those systems and not just individual
technologies but those but the Guild's
ecosystems of those technologies that
lead to closed-loop sustainability of
that system and then scalability of
those systems that is stuff that is
worth building so if you look at
building the future of our social
systems and knowing that the goal of our
social systems has to be aligning the
incentive of agents with the well-being
of other agents in the comments start
thinking about how to close the
incentive well-being gap how to close
the externality gap then building ways
to measure externalities and just see
them to then be able to quantify them
and internalize them those are
technologies worth building right to be
able to build a balance sheet of the
Commons the built world Commons the
natural world Commons to be able to have
data mined sources as well as repurpose
the IOT sensor systems to have real-time
sensor driven balance sheet of the
Commons right so then we can see where
the Commons are increasing and their
resilience versus decreasing where
they're decreasing what actions by what
you know players are involved in that
and you know how to really quantify it
those are things that should happen
starting to move towards things like
robotic automation of the shitty jobs
that does allow the ability to have
things like a Commonwealth economics
really start to emerge and then looking
at the accounting systems of how a
Commonwealth economics access based
systems rather than possession based
systems so when you start to think about
people's access to over rather than
owning a car if you had an uber system
where there were enough cars in close
proximity for peak time that's the total
amount of cars that have to be in the
system that's still something like that
20th of the amount of cars that are in
systems where people drive themselves in
the cars spend ninety five percent of
their time sitting that's a lot less
resource taken out of the earth for
actually more utility value safety etc
and the transportation system especially
as those part it becomes self-driving
and then all electric upgradeable and
then everyone can have access to the
highest transportation possible rather
than what you could afford previously
and your access to the resource doesn't
limit my access to the resource whereas
your possession would limit my access so
in a situation where there's a finite
amount of stuff and the less of it there
is the more value is added to it but not
real utility value right like even
though gold has some real utility value
as a as a conductor as a reflector we
don't use it for its utility value we
put it in bars and put it in a safe
where nobody really uses it for anything
at all other than representational value
based on its scarcity but we will damage
ecosystems that are actually supporting
our atmosphere and cleaning our water
and making pollinators work to get to
the goal right and because there's
enough air that I don't have any
differential value having some of it
over someone else there's no value so we
just keep ruining the out of it
so how to have a real valuation system
that is valuing proportional to real
value rather than you know nonsense
value that's about differential
advantage in competitive systems so
building those valuation systems you
know those are the kinds of things that
need to happen building the blockchain
kinds of technologies to post etherium
you know kinds of technologies that
allow non corruptible contracts and
currency and meta currency exchange and
governance right so in the social
systems these are all things that needs
to happen to bring another feature of
social system and worldview building
better systems of Education that
actually help develop children's innate
unique capacities and their intrinsic
incentive to thrive and experience life
fully and contribute to life fully
helping to develop and evolve those
education systems and then helping to
also develop media that gets to support
people with real information so the
future of sense-making systems and news
networks and you know educational
resources where information that is
trustworthy and relevant happens right
peer to peer vetting processes etc as
well as the right kinds of
psychotherapeutic processes for
reconditioning people that have went
through so much trauma and damage and
then being able to be in a position to
raise future humans with less damage
built world technologies that are
designed to evolve and support the
well-being of the humans in those
systems well being sustainable with the
planet rather than being cognizant of
only very few metrics they affect so
that means pain that isn't filled with
VOCs that are carcinogens and
neurotoxins and endocrine disruptors it
means paying attention to the kind of
lighting that's involved in all the
building materials etc for not just
aesthetics and the utility of keeping
rain off but for recognizing that if
humans are going to spend
90% of their time in built structures
how do you build those structures in a
way that is conditioning off the moment
human experience and predisposition of
the people who are in those so that kind
of intentional architecture and design
process so all of these are the kinds of
things that internalize externalities
that do more comprehensive design for
all that is affected close the causal
loops and don't just support something
being better within a self terminating
system but support the infrastructure
the core structures of new systems
emerging okay this is interesting a lot
of young people ask us for advice on
what they can do to contribute to a more
positive and sustainable future it seems
like from your framework closing loops
is the big answer and they can close
loops in any number of industries but
what would you add to that the fact of
them asking you the question is
something I would have them look at if
they are asking you what they can work
on to have their life be of greatest
value to life it's a great care and if
they understand you as people who have
studied things that are relevant to that
getting input is valuable to the degree
though that they are seeing US
authorities and they're looking for an
external authority to give them the
answer to what to do with their life
that thinking itself is one of the
things they have to overcome and if you
think about the way most people have
been raised as children we very rarely
got punished for doing what that
authorities wanted us to do and most all
of the times we got punished or for
doing things that we wanted to that
maybe appeal to our own sensibilities or
desires intuitions feelings and most of
the time that we got praised and
rewarded was for doing things the
authorities either wanted us to do or
you know we're at least aligned with
what they figured what we figured from
previous expressions they probably want
us to do and so this is a very deep
conditioning when we are most
susceptible to conditioning to look to
others to look to teachers and Sunday
school leaders and parents
you know authorities to tell us how to
live our lives and when we touched our
bodies we found that the parts of our
bodies that fell best to touch with the
parts that we got most in trouble for
touching
so obviously what feels good to us is
bad so we can't trust our feelings but
the authorities know that it's bad so we
can apparently trust the authorities but
not our feelings and no one has ever
really interested in our thoughts or
perspectives they were pre defined right
answers to things and we got praised
when we got them and we got in trouble
and we didn't get them and people were
not generally interested in our
aesthetic and design ideas they were
interested in us keeping clean things
that were someone else's design ideas
and so we got conditioned very deeply in
that system that is part of the system
that is self terminating because most
people are working at jobs that are
causing more net harm to the world than
benefit that they don't actually feel
good about but they do not trust their
own feeling or believe that they can do
something else or know how to actually
figure out what to do or believe in
themselves enough to self assess or self
initiate and most people when they look
at various situations in the world
actually feel really not okay with much
of the way the world is in ways that
come actually from love in them they
come from beauty in them even if
expressed as anger or jaded Ness but
they don't believe in their own ability
to find solutions to figure out so
they just numb out name them out on
alcohol or on TV or whatever they do and
so when you look at the people that have
ever meaningfully moved the world
forward where they solved some problems
that had not been solved it really
needed to be solved nobody taught them
how to do it because no one cooks the
problem wasn't solved yet nobody could
have taught Edison how to make a light
bulb nobody could have told Gandhi how
to get home roll for India and one of
the fascinating things was that they
decided to do it because they knew that
it was important before having any idea
how to do it and then they trusted in
both the rightness of it enough and
there
capability to learn enough to really
apply themselves deeply and to continue
through all of the early not successes
until they found stuff so what I would
encourage young people to do is to take
profound responsibility for their
existence and to know that there are a
lot of people in a lot of books and a
lot of courses that have valuable should
to teach them but if an adequate answer
to what they should do with their life
existed anywhere that whole thing would
be done already and the fact that the
things aren't done means that all the
best teachers and thinkers have not got
it yet right they have ideas they have
things to learn you should absolutely
learn from them and you're going to have
something to add not only in terms of
your work but also in terms of your
creativity so I would say look around at
the world and see all of the things that
really bother you and realize that them
bothering you as part of your guidance
and see all the things that you really
love all the things that are beautiful
and you realize they're connected right
animals are beautiful and then all of
the devastation of animals and their
habitat is really bothersome people are
beautiful so homelessness and or
bothersome right you children are
beautiful so bad education systems are
bothersome so look at what you love look
at how what you love is not well
supported in various areas and realize
that it does not have to be that way any
more than the world had to stay dark in
the time of Edison and yet for all of
human history before Edison it did right
and taking on something that seemed
impossible literally delivered the world
from darkness in that way right and then
study the out of the topic right
without thinking that a completely
adequate solution is there so there's
probably a lot of partially good
solutions maybe a technology that is
totally good technology but it hasn't
market feasibility hasn't came about yet
or the way to bring the meme out there
or parts of the ideas are there but they
need synthesized or whatever it is study
is a problem well study what an adequate
solution would look like gain a real
clear inside of what adequate solution
looks like in your own area of what you
care to contribute to
as things emerged that you feel like you
can contribute to as you're learning
about it contribute to them and continue
to assess on your own and initiate on
your own with of course good input from
all the places of good input that's the
key thing I would say take really deep
responsibility for the impact that you
have in your life while you're here and
then all of the study all the training
all the application that you need to
empower the kind of impact you want to
have make sure that happens
excellent advice right yeah Daniel thank
you for joining us this has been
enlightening yeah the thought that
you've done on all of these things is
fascinating it's a delight to be here
with you and when I see two intelligent
creative people who are looking at the
world and saying what is a vision of a
beautiful world that is commensurate to
our full capability and potential and
that is realistic and and grounded in
the face of our real capability and
potential and asking what you can do to
help bring about the positive versions
that feature helping to even get
positive visions of the future from
people who have thought about it well
and share those with people is an
incredible work and I'm delighted to see
this podcast what you're doing in that
delighted to be here with you on it
Thanks we're looking forward to chatting
with you again alright that's it for
this episode I hope you guys enjoyed it
thanks for listening if you want the
show notes they will be at future
thinkers dot org slash 36
this episode is brought to you by
eternity the Oracle machine eternity is
a new blockchain platform for smart
contracts with a token crowd sale
launching in March 2017 go to future
thinkers org slash eternity and
subscribe to their mailing list to get
notified when it goes live to get
notified of new podcasts and videos go
to future thinkers org and subscribe to
our mailing list you can also find us on
iTunes stitcher and you tube if you like
what we do and you want to help us make
more podcasts and videos give us a like
or you share it with your friends and
consider becoming a patron go to
patreon.com/crashcourse
cutting machinery org slash out
[Music]